Hello
Pratik!
AWS
COMPUTING!
AWS (Amazon Web Services) is a cloud computing platform that provides various services, including computing power, storage, databases, networking, AI/ML, IoT, and more. Since you've completed the AWS Cloud Technical Essentials course, you already have a basic understanding of AWS.

Key AWS Services You Should Know:
Compute Services

EC2 (Elastic Compute Cloud) → Virtual servers

Lambda → Serverless computing

Elastic Beanstalk → PaaS for deploying applications

Storage Services

S3 (Simple Storage Service) → Scalable object storage

EBS (Elastic Block Store) → Storage for EC2 instances

Glacier → Cold storage for backups

Database Services

RDS → Managed relational databases (MySQL, PostgreSQL, etc.)

DynamoDB → NoSQL database

Redshift → Data warehousing

Networking & Security

VPC → Virtual Private Cloud (networking setup)

Route 53 → Domain name system (DNS)

IAM → Identity and Access Management (user permissions)

DevOps & Monitoring

CloudWatch → Monitoring & logging

CloudFormation → Infrastructure as Code (IaC)

CodePipeline → CI/CD for automation

AI/ML & IoT

SageMaker → Machine learning service

Rekognition → Image & video analysis

IoT Core → IoT device management

Getting Started with AWS CLI
To interact with AWS from the Windows Terminal, install the AWS CLI and configure it:

Download AWS CLI: AWS CLI Installer

Configure AWS CLI:

sh
Copy
Edit
aws configure
Enter Access Key, Secret Key, Region, and Output Format.

Test AWS Connection:

sh
Copy
Edit
aws s3 ls
This lists S3 buckets if you have any.

How Can I Help?
Do you want to deploy something on AWS?

Do you need help with EC2, S3, or Lambda?

Are you looking for AWS certifications?